<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jamie Henson</title>
    <description>Full-stack developer and multi-instrumentalist, currently immersed in the wonders of San Francisco.</description>
    <link>http://jh47.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jh47.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 14:13:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The UK is turning into the US. And it shouldn&#39;t be.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Now, let me just start in saying that as far as politics go, I’m not exactly a passionate activist - I’m not going to pretend to be one all of a sudden as news of the recent election rolls off the press. But, here’s my two cents on the matter (or one penny via the current exchange rate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom worries me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, at least, not primarily because of the outcome of the recent election (it was awful on almost every front, whilst not entirely unexpected), but the mindset of a good chunk of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rising or falling any distance through the social ‘ranks’ in England is hard. It has its grounds in centuries-old civil and political infrastructure, and law. There is a class system. Always has been, and always will be whilst we remain a constitutional monarchy. If you’re born as a part of the working or the middle class, then unless you’re an outlier, you’ll die as a part of the working or the middle class. By the same token, if you’re born into acres of land and a fast-track to Eton, then there you shall remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British social structure is a collection of insoluble liquids in a tall, vertically-tapering beaker, with each liquid unable to mix with the others. Give it a good stir and globules can break off from their respective plateaus and fly all over the place, up or down or side to side, but they will never truly mix - despite the distance they’ve travelled. Eventually, given time, the system will revert to its original state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All people in early/mid adulthood are the blobs flying all over the beaker - trying to find their place in the scheme of things, and trying to mix in somewhere. I’m a blob currently a bit further from my origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The USA is simultaneously the most beautiful, and the ugliest country I have ever been to. It is constitutionally unburdened by the class system that is so engrained into the traditional fibres of British living, but at the same time it lacks the sensibilities or the common sense that makes Britain, in my view, a healthier place to live. Or at least, Britain at the moment. I can’t speak for how it’ll be in five years time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking objectively, the Conservatives have good and bad points. Labour aren’t the universally sparkling alternative, here and armed with a power-washer to scrub any blue-tinted stains from parliamentary seats. Their historic dismantling yesterday boldly showed (on Game of Thrones “Red Wedding” proportions) that they lacked conviction in demonstrating this. But every step the Conservatives take makes the UK more like the US. And I hate that. I don’t want to see the UK become this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USA works for the Americans. Here, money directly equates to power. With enough funding, and a US birth certificate, you could be President. You could do pretty much anything. Freedom: great. In a sandbox, this is actually the case, and the UK would comparatively be seen as antiquated and oppressive. But the reality doesn’t follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For America, the previously-mentioned beaker example contains not different layers of insoluble liquids that hold on to a rigid structure, but millions of tiny particles of sediment in one vast solution. Depending on their density (with the amount of money, education etc. inversely proportional to physical density), some float to the top, and others don’t. There is no layering here: if you sink to the bottom, there you lie. San Francisco is a big culprit of this. There is extreme wealth and staggering poverty within one snap of a camera’s lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, mix together the two beaker examples, and what do you get? A volatile mess. Where the lower layers sink to the bottom, and the upper layers rise to the top. The middle is caught in a vacuum, and disperses into dilution. People constrained by class, in a society where money shouts the loudest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What worries me is not necessarily the Conservatives themselves, but the willingness of people to opt-in for this path. To focus on the here and now and not consider where all this is going. When everything’s sold off, what then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m nowhere near politically knowledgeable enough to go into heavy detail on particular policies and such. I’m just commenting on what I am seeing, comparing where I am to where I came from, and looking at where that place is going. And right now, I don’t like it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 14:45:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2015/05/08/broken-britain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2015/05/08/broken-britain/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sisqo&#39;s Thong Song - a study into human nature</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Truly, one of the most poignant milestones for the turn of the millenium was the release of Mark Althavean Andrews’ (more widely known under his pen-name, Sisqo) magnum opus, Thong Song - which came out just before the final curtain fell, on December 31st, 1999. Its message is that of unbridled desire, and raw organic expression, compiled into the framework of a four-minute musical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sisqo starts by engaging the listener in a conversational tone, prefixing his parable with a brief soliloquy that directly references the carnal aspirations that most men are said to experience at some point in their lives, under the euphemistic context of “the finer things in life”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then wastes no time in setting the scene by outlining the physical attributes of the particular woman who has attracted his attention, primarily mentioning her “scandalous” taste in clothing, tendency to frequent “hip hop spots”, and how her actions wantonly inspire jealousy in Sisqo’s male peers. Sisqo deftly ties in a reference to a 1999 work by Ricky Martin, “Livin Da Vida Loca” [1], which offers an alternative socio-cultural commentary on the promiscuous and volatile nature of female members of the nighttime community that the artist frequents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As evidenced by his employment of hip hop instrumentation (with a twist of the baroque, as is his customary flair) and a utilitarian approach to song structure, Sisqo reveals himself to be quite the traditionalist. Thong Song has a central theme that Sisqo returns to frequently, and it is the emotional frame of reference that changes throughout as Sisqo increasingly comes to terms with his desires. Most of the lyrics (mainly for the purpose of expressing the desirability of his muse) have already been said by the first chorus, but it is after this point that the journey begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chorus is delivered with reserve: the calm before the storm. The focus is turned back on the narrator, who, for the first time, announces his aspirations. Since this is his first time saying the words out loud, Sisqo appears hesitant, unsure - he knows what he desires, but is not yet comfortable revealing his intentions publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this off his chest, Sisqo approaches the second verse with an enriched verve. The same words, but with more intensity, and by the second chorus, the audience can readily observe the personal development that Sisqo has already made. The second time, he is more expressive with his voice, recounting his aspirations with greater confidence and with a hint of aggression - a occasional side effect of real desire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the second release, the pace slows without cause, which leaves the listener at an impasse - is Sisqo going to take time to try to balance his outcries by pondering a neutralising counter-argument, or will he indulge himself further and more deeply explore his feelings? Indeed, it is the latter. Sisqo breaks the emotional armistice by bringing in both a key-change, and multiple repetitions of the chorus - whilst seemingly forgoing lyrical storytelling for a pure vocalisation of his core desire - to “see that thong”. Seemingly content with the extent of his message’s deliverance, Sisqo maintains this heightened intensity to the close, allowing the listener time to reflect on the emotional gravity previously expressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is ambiguous as to what Sisqo’s motivation is in terms of his source of satisfaction. Considering the conflicting theories of J. S. Mill [2], and G. E. Moore [3], Sisqo may either expect to gain pleasure specifically from the attainment of “that thong”, or, he may already experience pleasure via his desire - and so attaining “that thong” would only serve to validate his satisfaction. Referencing Kant [4], pleasure may simply and sufficiently derive from Sisqo passively witnessing a figure he finds beautiful, meaning that Thong Song serves as nought but a powerful tribute. Conversely, following Hume [5], his desire may act as the catalyst that, permitting that he personally believes that “that thong” is attainable, drives him to take action in a way that is not disclosed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a counterpoint, one can conclude that Sisqo has no long term motivation and that whether or not he acquired “that thong” is immaterial - he is simply voicing his emotional range about a topic that is not grounded around any physical event, but is instead a theoretical construct of an event that he, and others of his peer group and target demographic, can relate to. Therefore, in this context, the psychological applications of Moore et al. can be directed onto the listener themselves, abstracting Sisqo into the role of a social commentator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On an ending note, Thong Song has different meaning depending on the personal beliefs and aspirations of the listener. One can either objectively take Sisqo’s account for an individual expression of organic, raw desire, purely from the perspective of the narrator - or they can use Thong Song as a conduit for their own feelings, and extrapolate its message onto their own lives. Either way, this work was undeniably a potent endnote in the millenium it played a part in concluding.
 
&lt;em&gt;**
 &lt;/em&gt;References:
1) Morales, E. M. (1999). Ricky Martin. Columbia Records.
2) Mill, J. S. (1865). Principles of political economy: with some of their applications to social philosophy (Vol. 2). Longmans, Green.
3) Moore, G. E. (1903). Principia Ethica.
4) Kant, I. (1790). Critique of judgement.
5) Hume, D. (1738). A treatise of human nature.*&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 08:45:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2015/04/19/thong-song/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2015/04/19/thong-song/</guid>
        
        <category>thong</category>
        
        <category>song</category>
        
        <category>sisqo</category>
        
        <category>psychology</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Freedom for Wrists</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s been a lot of buzz around here, and generally around the world, about the Apple Watch. The latest chapter in “Classic Apple” of them taking something that has already existed for a while, and selling their shiny, well-formed shot at it as “revolutionary” while asking a price that would get any Android alternative laughed out of the park. It is what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wider topic of digital wearables has been a sticking point in my mind for a while. I bought a Moto 360, to see what it would be like. And after a few weeks, I sold it. Most of that time, it was sitting in its dock, charging on my windowsill. This isn’t a backhanded statement on the device’s battery life, not this time, the battery life was surprisingly high given the reviews I’d read. It was the form factor. I hated wearing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to approach a smartwatch. The primary one is that of an augmentation to your smartphone (which it has to be tethered to, to get any real use out of it), for situations where you can’t dig your phone out of your pocket, for whatever first-world problem reason. I had notifications instantly on my wrist, accompanied by a spirited vibration with each one, but I didn’t want to do anything with them. I wasn’t going to answer a message with a vague emoticon, nor was I going to entrust the contents of a message to the mercy of voice recognition - not to mention the fact that I didn’t want to be “that guy” who talks to his devices in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here comes the wider point - I don’t like being “plugged in” all the time. As a software developer who spends his time in front of some screen or other for the majority of his waking hours, I don’t want to be constantly prodded by some little jumped-up sundial when I clock off. I want out. No form factor, no matter how sleek and aluminium-y, is going to change that. My old watch, a £10 digital from Argos, told the time, and voiced an alarm when I told it to. That’s it. And my phone, which hoovers up news from a whole plethora of services (and does a pretty good job of grouping and prioritising them for quick reading), can be left on a desk or checked every now and then. The whole point of a smartwatch is that you wear it. It’s there all the time. And that’s horrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not against all wearables. Only ones that try and bring the entire infosphere to your wrist. Fitness trackers and the like do their limited job-set well. And, of course, the other side to this is that I’m being counter-revolutionary and being “that guy” who opposes change when in five years everyone’s going to be wearing these bloody things. Everyone has a smartphone now, when critics before would have said the exact same thing, claiming that the desktop computer was enough. No doubt people hated on the printing press, when the renaissance loom was enough. And the renaissance loom? An unnecessary distraction from cave paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a cultural thing. Things move on and change, but at the moment I don’t see a lot of good in smartwatches. Especially for an asking price of $300. Especially for an asking price in the tens of thousands or however much that silly top-of-the-range Apple Watch is. But it’s not the money, it’s another digital mouth to feed. Both with a daily charging routine, and your life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 10:18:32 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2015/04/09/Freedom-for-wrists/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2015/04/09/Freedom-for-wrists/</guid>
        
        <category>wearables</category>
        
        <category>apple watch</category>
        
        <category>moto 360</category>
        
        <category>watch</category>
        
        <category>smartwatch</category>
        
        <category>freedom</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>(Maybe) Halfway</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a good three months since my last instalment and a lot has happened. A notable theme last time was that of indecision and the slightly uneasy feeling of living between two highly positive parts of the world. That feeling still remains, although it has manifested itself under new grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the start of February I went back home to see family, friends, and old places. I won’t go into the details but the trip was immensely helpful - one of its purposes was to allow me to compare the two lives side by side, to see what I preferred looking long-term. In short, it was a lovely visit, mostly because it was a nourishing taste of stability and familiarity, with a taste of gimpery. And gigs. Those too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressing issue now is that of what to do next, and how I should conduct myself here. Visa depending, my life as a US resident could be over in a few months, or could continue for another couple of years - it’s that ambiguity that sets aside this experience from a year-abroad at Uni, for instance. It means the difference between choosing which side of the Atlantic to focus on, which is important. SF, as I’ve learned so far, is not a place you can half-heartedly coast through. And as two 11-hour flights recently reaffirmed to me - that ocean is bloody huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;code-uber-alles&lt;/em&gt; lifestyle is a lot to keep on top of - I’m not averse to working hard, but for me it was always about maintaining a healthy balance between having a creative outlet and getting work done, and at times combining the two. Here, the power that the tech industry has over all facets of life is awe-inspiring. I went to part of the LAUNCH Hackathon yesterday and everything, from the contestants, to the location, to the prizes, was immense. For those who eat, drink and breathe code, it was Mecca. I cannot imagine something of that scale ever happening anywhere in the UK. And this stuff happens all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing - the definition of what’s “cool” in technology is very different here to anywhere else I’ve been. Here, “cool” is taking an on-the-surface boring (but highly functional) idea, dolling it up with snazzy branding and a wall of merchandise, and throwing it out to the masses for free. This is how innovation happens, by taking real problems and approaching them with an agile, nothing-to-lose mindset and a view towards establishing and growing a community. And because these cutting-edge tools are finding their way into commercial practice (my job included), it means I no longer have to slave over a monolithic tower of Java because some archaic business license says so - which is definitely a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to my free time though, I’d much rather tinker with a toaster to try and make it generate music. Nobody would ever buy the outcome, and you wouldn’t see it on a .io domain, but it’s a bit of fun. And that’s the thing, when hobbyist coding is culturally strong-armed into joining some open-source crusade with a larger agenda, it’s a noble cause, but it smudges the line between work and recreation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steering back towards lifestyle, over the past few months I’ve adjusted much more to actually living here. It took a trip back to the UK to realise that the Americans do some things better, and the Brits do some things better. The weather is definitely in the camp of the former. Cadbury’s chocolate is now only in the camp of the latter, thanks to Hershey’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway. To conclude: things are alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Superbowl sucked. Oh God, did it suck.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2015/03/01/halfway/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2015/03/01/halfway/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Three months in SF - but there&#39;s always room for Bristol</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been here for about three months now - just long enough (I’d say) to claim that the transition has been made from this feeling like a short trip to this feeling like a full move. And with that, the realisation that I most likely won’t return to the UK for just under a year has made me miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bristol is a wonderful city with a strong pulse. I don’t miss the University per se, but the city itself, and the people I met during University who still live there, either at Uni or in the working life. I was ready to graduate and move away from academia, having done my part and received my grade. But I’ve found it increasingly hard moving from such an active musical lifestyle to having nothing. I keep up playing music as a hobby, yes, but there isn’t that community, that outlet to play it publicly, and enjoy it with others, friends, who are into the same thing as you. At least, I haven’t found it yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are different in America. It’s not better than the UK, and it’s not worse. It’s just different. It’s interesting noting cultural differences - there’s a different conversational style, a different sense of humour, different social expectations. British conversation staples such as the weather, laced with a touch of self-deprecation are lost on the Americans, whereas several American nuances of a more direct approach are lost on me. We share (or rather, they’ve inherited) a language, but conversation isn’t usually as fluid as with my British counterparts - naturally because I’ve been a part of one culture for 22 years, and the other for a mere three months. There’s a lot to pick up on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously in my life the run up to Christmas has always followed a sort of loose routine, but here the traditions and even the environment (it’s still basically Summer, for a start) are rather set apart from what I’m used to. Ordinarily it’s a time to spend with family, whereas I’m not able to do that this year. In short, I’m a little out of my comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the difficulties, that’s okay. One should rattle things up in their early twenties. It’s Thanksgiving today, and despite never acknowledging it as a holiday before I’m getting into the feel of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a joy to live in SF. I really like being involved and present in a place where the next big thing is just waiting to emerge, along with countless other ideas bubbling under the surface. Bristol is vibrant and creative too, but SF has much more cultural diversity (it’s a lot bigger). That said, SF also feels much more anonymous. More turbocharged. One of the main things I love about Bristol vs. cities like London is how naturally laid back it is. There’s a lot going on, but it’s all happening at a pace that never feels uncomfortable or overly urgent. It feels more harmonious than SF, which suffers from a bit of a gulf between groups of individuals within notably variant pay brackets, to put it one way. Maybe, for cultural differences outlined above, a Californian native would feel the same friction living in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have said to me that SF feels like a small city, despite its breadth and size. I can agree with that, it feels a lot smaller now than the daunting metropolis it resembled when I first arrived - and I was still encountering new places in Bristol at the same rate four years on as when I arrived as a fresher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a life in two places, and a whopping great stretch of water does its part to ensure that they don’t overlap. While I’m progressing headlong through one, having a great time doing it, I’m still holding onto the other. God Save The Queen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 02:17:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2014/11/27/three-months/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2014/11/27/three-months/</guid>
        
        <category>abroad</category>
        
        <category>america</category>
        
        <category>bristol</category>
        
        <category>sf</category>
        
        <category>uk</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Streamer Wars (Spotify, Google and Rdio)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For me, Spotify was always the king when it came to music streaming. I was an early adopter, and I loved it - because it offered something new and exciting, in a whole different way. These days, my praise for the service has wained - there are several wolves at the gates and many of the canine contenders have nifty tricks up their furry sleeves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried a few out. All operated on a similar fundamental level (same bitrates, catalogue sizes, price etc), but had distinct ups and downs when comparing useful features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spotify&lt;/strong&gt; is still highly competent: it offers a huge collection, high performance delivery, and very good social integration (take it or leave it) with third-party apps extending the existing offerings. But I found that the radio service I previously loved was starting to churn out the same old stuff, and that the app hadn’t really advanced functionally in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an Android user, I tried &lt;strong&gt;Google Music All Access&lt;/strong&gt; first, finding that it solved all the problems Spotify posed, whilst taking away some of its good points. Its catalogue is massive, but it is unique in its ability to allow you to fill in the gaps by uploading your own music to the mix. Also, the radio is excellent - intelligent, fresh, and very well implemented. Furthermore, perhaps somewhat unsurprisingly, Google’s service offers exemplary Chromecast support - allowing slick usage of the little stick from both mobile and desktop devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Google has poor social integration (it doesn’t natively interface with any other services, even Last.fm). There is no native desktop client, and while there are unofficial options (such as the plain-but-functional G-Ear Player and the Google-esque but currently buggy Radiant Player), there isn’t that uniform desktop presence that made Spotify so pervasive. It was also very difficult to migrate playlists from other services to Google’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between Google and Spotify was &lt;strong&gt;Rdio&lt;/strong&gt;, combining the positives of both of the other two services, but not doing either side as well. It has a desktop client, a good radio service, Chromecast support, and excellent social integration (better than Spotify’s). However, both the mobile apps and the Chromecast support are annoyingly unreliable. I couldn’t get the service to stream from my laptop, and while the stream worked from my phone it would frequently cut out. And most annoyingly, there is no “Play Next” feature, making impromptu party playlisting a very disjoined affair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, Rdio (to me) looks the nicest. It has a very fresh and clean interface and and was a very easy switch from Spotify whereas the home-grown desktop clients for Google Music were a bit clunky. Rdio also has the advantage of offering a family plan - meaning much lesser costs for groups of 5 or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, none of the big players are perfect. &lt;strong&gt;Spotify&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;popular&lt;/strong&gt; but needs to &lt;strong&gt;be more inventive&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Google&lt;/strong&gt; has the &lt;strong&gt;tech&lt;/strong&gt; but needs to &lt;strong&gt;play more nicely with others&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Rdio&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;strong&gt;pleasant blend&lt;/strong&gt; of the two and &lt;strong&gt;cost-effective for groups&lt;/strong&gt;, but is plagued by &lt;strong&gt;technical issues&lt;/strong&gt;. You won’t be disappointed with any of them - just pick the service that caters best to your needs. For me, I may as well stick with Spotify - as I’m already invested in the service and old Spots can still throw its weight amongst the others. However, with the recent announcement of &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtube-global.blogspot.com/2014/11/youtube-music-2014.html&quot;&gt;YouTube Music Key&lt;/a&gt;, it’s definitely worth keeping an eye on the Google camp.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 23:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2014/11/12/streamers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2014/11/12/streamers/</guid>
        
        <category>google</category>
        
        <category>music</category>
        
        <category>rdio</category>
        
        <category>spotify</category>
        
        <category>streaming</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Enter: The Bransion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today marks a month of living in San Francisco, the transition from nervously waiting in Heathrow Terminal 3 for the first of the other SVIP members to arrive, to sitting on my bed with a cold (intriguingly 50¢ a can) beer, looking out of my bedroom window that offers a spectacular view of eastern SF and the Bay. A lot of goings-on are framed in this one scene - the perpetually busy Bay Bridge, the looming towers of SoMa and Market, and the heavily Latin-influenced Mission District. It really puts home that this is a city with a lot about it, that if you were to more closely examine any part of what’s in view then you’d find something new. Many major cities have this potential I suppose, but it’s rare that you’re able to realise it so completely from such a macroscopic viewpoint. I liked my old house in Bristol, but my room overlooked a trainline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things I’ve learned this month: Google deliver groceries, people aren’t lying when they say that Comcast are rubbish, Venmo is the future, it is indeed possible to get English tea easily, and that one should be very wary of Folsom Street on one particular weekend in September. Only one of the above discoveries involves four blocks of leather-clad men whipping each other and enthusiastically sampling each other’s fleshy parts. A further hint, it’s not part of Google’s delivery service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend we left the StartupHouse, a “hacker house” (in reality an industrial complex converted into a ~50-person communal living space) in the heart of SoMa. On a temporary basis, the place was fine - the lack of any private space or room for personal possessions wore thin after a time but long-term living was never its intended function. The tradeoff to compromised living standards (most notably, the orchestra of nightly snoring) was the advantage that communal living provides - an ever-shifting set of relatively like minded people from all over the world. I even saw a talk there by the CEO of Unity, which was both unexpected, and seriously cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scoring lucky on Craigslist (wait until you read the whole sentence before you infer things from that), and tremendous support from SVIP itself, we managed to bag a house for five that was so big, we were able to get a sixth guy in just to fill the place. SF’s housing market is brutal, and since we wanted to keep our large group together, our pickings were on the order of fingers on one hand. SVIP provided a loan for the hefty deposit, and essentially enabled us to get the place we wanted - it realistically wouldn’t have been possible without them. It’s that level of support that makes me seriously thankful for the opportunity that has come my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to the present, work is still tough but it’s a learning process. With every day comes a new area to learn about, in a way that is significantly more accelerated and less incubated than a University environment as the changes I make affect real people in real time, and there’s no quantified marking scheme. I still maintain that University is more beneficial in preparing you to work under punishing time restraints with ever-changing criteria than it is for what it teaches you in a purely academic sense. You can acquire the raw knowledge anywhere, but the opportunity to employ it in a constructive environment, you cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, it has been an incredible month so far. All of us on the SVIP have built ourselves a platform on which to move forward and encounter new things - it’s rather exciting indeed to consider what things they might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I finally bought a guitar, which means that all of my essential home comforts are now fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jh47.com/img/view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2014 21:52:13 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2014/09/28/svip2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2014/09/28/svip2/</guid>
        
        <category>moving</category>
        
        <category>san francisco</category>
        
        <category>sf</category>
        
        <category>svip</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Land of the free</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, I’m finally here! Five months ago, I received a piece of news that rendered me both speechless and giddily excited. And then just one week ago, I was very, very tired having just got off an 11 hour flight, but no less enthused. For the past week, San Francisco has been my home, and will be for the next 55 - give or take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back before University I remember always wanting to go to the States - Bristol’s year abroad program was part of the reason I chose it (even though I ended up not going in the end). Last year a mate on my course applied for the Silicon Valley Internship Program (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.siliconvalleyinternship.com/&quot;&gt;SVIP&lt;/a&gt;) and I must say I didn’t give it much thought at the time. That was until he got onto the scheme, and then suddenly my indifference elevated to “Shit. I want to do that!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this year I applied, and after months of gruelling interviews, knockout stages and a Google’s-worth of prep I too made it onto the programme, at (as luck would have it) the same company as my fellow ex-Bristolian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got the news I couldn’t quite believe it, I literally couldn’t (and still can’t) think of a better way to progress after University than this - an opportunity to work for a year in Silicon Valley with a startup at the cutting edge of their area. Tech Mecca. Tekker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve only been to America once before, and while that too was technically &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.umich.edu/nime2012/Proceedings/papers/131_Final_Manuscript.pdf&quot;&gt;on business&lt;/a&gt;, I wasn’t able to really live in the same shoes as a resident. I’m not saying that I’m one-of-the-gang in San Francisco just yet, but I’ve already moved away from the tourist mould in that I’ve been about in parts that tourists probably wouldn’t see. And I won’t omit this part either - it hasn’t been easy so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though jetlag has long stopped being an issue, we (as in me and the other members of the SVIP cohort) have been going to bed routinely before 11 in the week. The days are long, but not because of tedium - but because there’s a hell of a lot to do and because we all have a huge amount to learn. Plus, as California is so massive it takes a good while to get to work. It’s astounding really, I suppose I’ll feel even better soon when I can actually contribute to the company I’m working for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another source of difficulty was more emotional than physical. Coming here involved saying a lot of goodbyes, some rather painful, but the emotion was diffused somewhat with the realisation that they wouldn’t be completely disconnected from me, nor me from them. In this day and age it’s actually a challenge to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be able to contact someone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the positives, oh man. The city is very impressive, even at a glance. Regions change so much, and there’s great things to see in each. This is just an intro post - I’ll write more about SF when I feel well-versed enough to actually comment about it. As an indication of the vibe here though, on my first day I stumbled upon a Filipino food festival with a performer singing and ukulele-ing about the difficulties of being in a relationship with a vegetarian. And the moments have rolled in since!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Despite all the merits, the tea here just isn’t the same. This pains me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 07:08:31 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2014/09/05/svip1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2014/09/05/svip1/</guid>
        
        <category>francisco</category>
        
        <category>san</category>
        
        <category>svip</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Final Project: week one</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a week since the end of my January deadline onslaught, so after a couple of days of recovery I set towards starting the project that’s set to take over the entirety of this term. For one of the units last term, Interactive Devices, I kept a “blog” of sorts, which documented my progress throughout the mini-project. I found it helpful, so I thought I would try it here as well. Here goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it in its simplest terms, I’m building a reverse musical visualiser. Something that takes any visual input, whether that be from a film, a game, or a person’s general activity on a computer screen, and converts it into music that somehow represents that activity. The purpose is mainly for individuals who are creating visual media, and want to test how certain types of soundtrack would fit with the content - for example a film maker who hasn’t chosen their sound yet, or a game developer who’s making a procedurally-generated game. I don’t actually have a name yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did was to break down music into its seven constituent parts: Dynamics, Tempo, Timbre, Rhythm, Melody, Harmony and Texture. I then decided how each of those parts would be represented inside my generation algorithms. The less-subjective parts of music (tempo, texture, timbre and dynamics) were easy to map to a set of visual features. The dynamics and texture would depend on the global rate of change of pixel colours, the timbre would depend on the types of colours that had high activity, and the tempo dependent on rhythmic spikes. But the melody, harmony and rhythm are going to be more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There lies another set of questions that fundamentally underpin my program’s functionality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where will the input be - through a camera, or on-screen?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the music be generated completely via visual features, or will the features control parameters of a template piece?
The answer to the first is easy - on screen. The noise introduced via a camera feed would be too much, and it goes against the true purpose and intention of my application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to the second is a matter of accuracy vs. practicality, and one that will probably surface after another week’s worth of development. My feeling already though is that the priority is a fluid and appealing demo, and so the lack of distinguishing features in a desktop stream may result in a very bland piece of music. Therefore, the second option may be more appealing - to have the visual features control an underlying skeletal structure. But I’ll go more into that after I’ve done some research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With respect to the actual application itself, I have so far written a Python program that takes a pixel map of the whole screen via the QT framework, divides it into colour-matched blocks, and counts the blocks. I can watch this mapping via a display maintained by the PyGame framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basis for this was a Python bot that could play Bejeweled, as the basis of the bot was fast colour detection on-screen. I changed it by stripping out all of the mouse manipulation controls, and significantly enhancing the colour detection algorithms. My first foray into Python, so going well so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue was cross-compatibility. It worked flawlessly in Linux, but it straight up didn’t work in Windows or Mac. I swapped out “autopy” for PyQt, which was both faster and allowed Windows to play. I tried swapping out PyGame for Pyglet to allow 64-bit compatibility, but it didn’t work how I wanted it to - as in, the “app lock” thing was really problematic. PyGame has plentiful support, and it just worked. So Mac will have to wait for now. The issue with Mac was that PyQt needed to be 64 bit for some reason, and PyGame only works in 32 bit. Crapple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 22:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2014/02/02/final-project-week-one/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2014/02/02/final-project-week-one/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Interactive Devices: Wrapping Up</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the past two months, I, along with two others, have developed a musical interface from scratch, using commonly available parts and software tools. We started by brainstorming with simple notes and ideas, and ended with a fully fledged prototype that we performed with in front of our class and lecturers. I have been keeping a blog throughout this whole process, which describes each of the stages in greater detail (a complete list of posts available &lt;a href=&quot;http://jh47.com/category/university/interactive-devices/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), but in this post I will wrap up what we did, as a rounded conclusion to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;span-styleline-height-15emcoming-up-with-waves-to-wavesspan&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;Coming up with Waves To Waves&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;As I said in the opening paragraph, we started with nothing - coming together with a stack of Post-It notes and a small amount of time to fire out ideas to each other. We all knew that we wanted to do a musically-oriented project due to our respective musically-involved backgrounds and interests, but that was it. We started with ~30 ideas, ranging from the feasible to the comparatively ridiculous - but at that stage, no idea was a bad idea, as all steps helped to bring us closer to the final topic. Eventually, we narrowed it down to around four primary ideas, ranging from a tangible speaker that you physically manipulate to alter the sound, to a three-dimensional laser based instrument that uses fog as an interactive medium. However, we all settled on the concept of a “water-based musical interface”, a small handful of words that would eventually turn into Waves To Waves (&lt;strong&gt;WTW&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we had one idea, we set about refining it, narrowing down the scope so that we could specifically say what parts we needed, and how we would build it. This wasn’t a one-time process, as our &lt;a href=&quot;http://jh47.com/2013/10/finalidea/&quot;&gt;first final idea candidate&lt;/a&gt; was notably different to what we ended up with - starting with a row of buoyant balls that are tracked by a Kinect as they bob up and down on the water as the surface is disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WTW as it is today came about after discussions with Pete Bennett and Paul Worgan, who are researchers in the University of Bristol BIG lab with an active interest in musical interfaces. We initially pitched WTW as a large installation with a strong expressive performance element and a strong mathematical foundation (that literally turned physical waves into sound waves via a one-to-one mapping), but Pete and Paul recommended that we go down a more user-friendly, collaborative route. Taking on board their advice, we down-scaled WTW to something that could “fit in a backpack” (it can), and placed the focus more around ease of use and a pleasing audible result, instead of an accurate mathematical simulation of wave mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-the-prototype&quot;&gt;Developing the prototype&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point in the design process, we knew actually what we _wanted _to build. It was just a matter of building it. Before starting however, we needed to gain more experience with the tools we aimed to use, and so each of us spent a week learning how to use the Arduino, and how to use Pure Data. This was a valuable step as it allowed us to step ahead more wisely by knowing the advantages and the pitfalls of the tools we were using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WTW purposefully has a very simple and cheap construction. The “water tank” is a storage container bought from Wilkinsons, the sensors were bought for ~£4 a piece off eBay, and the wooden frame was constructed from some wood sitting in the garden of my student house. Also, a friend of ours, Tom Mortensson, kindly allowed us to borrow some of his 3-pin cables for hooking up the sensors to the Arduino, as well as a sensor shield for making interfacing more of a plug-and-play operation. Nonetheless, the final product comes together quite well, and proves how you don’t have to have a large budget to build a functioning musical interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_661” align=”aligncenter” width=”680”]&lt;a href=&quot;http://jh47.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/2013-12-08-16.35.14.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jh47.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/2013-12-08-16.35.14-1024x757.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The final Waves To Waves prototype&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The final Waves To Waves prototype[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-the-performance&quot;&gt;Preparing the performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we had what was basically a complete product (in a physical sense) by the start of December, we looked towards preparing a performance, and tweaking WTW so that it functioned better within a live environment. We experimented with playing it collaboratively with other instruments. We experimented with different musical styles and sounds. Essentially, we strove to explore what water lent itself best to as a transmissive medium for a musical instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found that due to the lack of precision of both the movement capabilities of water, and the inexpensive water depth sensors we had purchased, WTW wasn’t suited to fill the role of an instrument designed to play a melodic line. Instead, similarly to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.umich.edu/nime2012/Proceedings/papers/131_Final_Manuscript.pdf&quot;&gt;Kugelschwung &lt;/a&gt;(an older project of mine that also used a cumbersome mechanic for generating music), we decided to have WTW generate ambient soundscapes that played more of a supportive role in a wider musical arrangement. Therefore, for the debut musical performance, we employed two keyboard synthesisers to create a fully-textured musical performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Footage of this debut performance (embedded in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jh47.com/2013/12/performing/&quot;&gt;previous &lt;/a&gt;Interactive Devices post) is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/81500664&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-the-paper-and-video&quot;&gt;Preparing the paper and video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having scope for six pages, we found the CHI paper layout to be relatively restrictive in terms of how much we could actually include, and so we had to be rather selective in what we included in the paper. Thus, we thought it was primarily important to include these sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An introduction to the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A brief review of previous articles of related academic literature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An overview of the hardware and software behind Waves To Waves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A discussion on how it fits within the wider HCI community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A discussion on how Waves To Waves could be expanded to further our concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the paper does a good job of describing the past, present and future of Waves To Waves, it doesn’t show it in action - and so this is where the affiliated video fills a valuable gap. We aimed to make the video as approachable as possible, by presenting it in a similar style to how we presented the interface to peers and lecturers on the 10th of December. Below is said demonstration video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/82002186&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thoughts-on-how-we-did-as-a-group&quot;&gt;Thoughts on how we did as a group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the project, James, Ben and I were all good friends, and so working together was painless since we already knew what each of our skills and preferences were, and since we felt we could be completely honest with each other during design discussions. Furthermore, despite initially feeling at a disadvantage, we felt that working in a three was actually preferable to working in a larger group (the average group size was five), since there was less of an overhead from team management, and less conflict from design disputes. We kept a very agile working form, kept constant communication, and ensured that each of us had a job to do - where progress was constantly and immediately reported. Moreover, we met and worked together regularly - as our smaller group size meant that collectively we were more flexible in terms of how we worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of our performance as a group I have no regrets or criticisms. All members of the team pulled their weight equally, and all added valuable contributions which pushed the project forward. I took the lead on the software that sat between the interface and the proprietary synthesiser that generated the sound, James took the lead on the video, and Ben took the lead on the paper - with each of us contributing in all areas to varying degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parting word on this project is that it truly has been a lot of fun - in a world of strict assignments and theoretical rigidity, it was refreshing to get free rein to make something I actually wanted to make, employing my existing technical and musical knowledge. Since I’m very interested in musical interfaces, and indeed music itself, I feel that I learned more in this assignment by exploring technologies and methods in my own time than I would have by reading a textbook or a series of papers on topics I care little for. Thus, I would heartily recommend this unit to any current third year Computer Science students at Bristol, especially if you’re creatively minded. It’s a rare opportunity to put a little of yourself into the work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2013 21:52:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jh47.com/2013/12/19/wrappingup/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jh47.com/2013/12/19/wrappingup/</guid>
        
        <category>arduino</category>
        
        <category>conclusion</category>
        
        <category>design process</category>
        
        <category>interactive devices</category>
        
        <category>project</category>
        
        <category>waves to waves</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
